Chapter 40 midnight folks harpineers and sailors.
Forcel rises and discovers the watch standing, lounging, leaning, and lying
in various attitudes, all singing in chorus.
Farewell and adue to you, Spanish ladies. Farewell and adue to you ladies
of Spain. Our captains commanded first Nantucket sailor. Oh boys, don't be
sentimental. It's bad for the digestion.
Take a tonic and follow me. Sings and all follow. Our captain stood upon the
deck, a spy glass in his hand, a viewing of those gallant whales that blew at
every strand. Oh, your tubs and your boats, my boys, and by your braces
stand, and we'll have one of those fine whales, hand boys overhand. So be
cheery, my lads, may your hearts never fail, while the bold harpooner is
striking the whale. Mate's voice from the quarter deck. Eight bells there
forward. Second Nantucket sailor. I've asked the chorus. Eight bells there. Do
you hear bell boy? Strike the bell.
Eight thou pip, thou blackling. And let me call the watch. I have the sort of
mouth for that. The hogs head mouth. So, so thrusts his head down the scuttle.
Starbolines. Ahoy. Eight bells there below. Tumble up. Dutch sailor.
Grand snoozing tonight. Matey. fat night for that. I mark this in our old mogul's
wine. It's quite deadening to some asps.
We sing, they sleep. I lie down there like ground tear butts. Adam again
there. Take this copper pump and hail them through it. Tell them to a vast
dreaming of their lasses. Tell them it's the resurrection that they must kiss
their last and come to judgment. That's the way. That's it. Thy throat ain't
spoiled with eating Amsterdam butter.
French sailor hist boys, let us have a jig or two before we ride to anchor in
blanket bay. What say ye? There comes the other watch. Stand by all legs. Pip,
little pip, harrah with your tambourine.
Pip, sulky and sleepy. Don't know where it is. French sailor, beat thy belly
then, and wag thy ears. Jigot men I say marries the word harrah damn me won't
you dance form now Indian file and gallop into the double shuffle throw
yourselves legs legs Iceland sailor I don't like your floor matey it's too
springy to my taste I'm used to ice floors I'm sorry to throw cold water on
the subject but excuse me maltise sailor me too where's your girls who but The
fool would take his left hand by his right and say to himself, "How do you do
partners? I must have partners."
Sicilian sailor. I girls and a green.
Then I'll hop with you. Yay. Turn grasshopper.
Long Island sailor. Well, well, yes, sulkis. There's plenty more of us. Ho
corn when you may, say I. All legs go to harvest soon. Ah, here comes the music.
Now for it, Azor sailor, ascending and pitching the tambourine up the scuttle.
Here you are, Pip, and there's the windless bits. Up you mount. Now, boys,
the half of them dance to the tambourine. Some go below. Some sleep or
lie among the coils of rigging. Oaths a plenty. Azor sailor dancing. Go to it,
Pip. Bang it, bellboy. Rig it, dig it, Stig it. Quig it, bellboy. Make
fireflies. Break the jinglers.
Pip. Jinglers. You say? There goes another dropped off. I pound it. So,
China sailor, rattle thy teeth then, and pound away. Make a pagod of thyself.
French sailor. Merry mad. Hold up thy hoop pip till I jump through it. Split
jibs. Tear yourselves.
Pashego quietly smoking. That's the white man. He calls that fun. Humph. I
save my sweat. Old man sailor. I wonder whether those jolly lads bethink them of
what they are dancing over. I'll dance over your grave. I will. That's the
bitterest threat of your night women that beat headwinds round corners. Oh
Christ, to think of the green navies and the green skull crew. Well, well, we
like the whole world's a ball, as you scholars have it, and so it is right to
make one ballroom of it. Dance on, lads.
You're young. I was once.
Third, Nantucket sailor. Spell. Oh, this is worse than pulling after whales in a
calm. Give us a whiff, Tash. They cease dancing and gather in clusters.
Meantime, the sky darkens. The wind rises. Laskcar sailor by Brahma boys
it'll thou sail soon the skyborn high tide ganges turn to wind thou show us
thy black brow sa maltise sailor reclining and shaking his
cap it's the waves the snow caps turn to jig it now they'll shake their tassels
soon now would all the waves were women then I'd go drown and chassis with them
ever more there's not so sweet On earth, heaven may not match it as those swift
glances of warm wild bosoms in the dance when the over arboring arms hide such
ripe bursting grapes.
Sicilian sailor reclining. Tell me not of it. Hark ye lad. Fleet interlacings
of the limbs, li swayings, coyings, flutterings, lip, heart, hip, all grays,
unceasing touch and go. Not taste, observe ye, else come sitty, a pagan,
nudging. Tahesian sailor, reclining on a mat. Hail holy nakedness of our dancing
girls, the hea. Ah low veiled high palm Tahiti. I still rest me on thy mat but
the soft soil has slid. I saw thee woven
in the wood my mat green the first day I brought ye thence now worn and wilted
quite. Ah me not thou nor I can bear the change. How then if so be transplanted
to yawn sky. Here I the roaring streams from Pirohiti's peak of spears when they
leap down the crags and drown the villages. The blast, the blast up spine
and meet it. Leaps to his feet.
Portuguese sailor. How the sea rolls swashing against the side. Stand by for
reefing hearties. The winds are just crossing swords. Pel they go lunging presently.
Danish sailor. Crack, crack, old ship.
So long as thou crackest, thou holdest.
Well done. The mate there holds you to it stiffly. He's no more afraid than the
isle fort at Katagot, put there to fight the Baltic with stormlashed guns on
which the sea salt cakes. Fourth Nantucket sailor. He has his orders,
mind you that. I heard old Ahab tell him he must always kill a squall, something
as they burst a water spout with a pistol. Fire your ship right into it.
English sailor blood. But that old man's a grand old cove. We are the lads to
hunt him up his whale. All I old man sailor.
How the three pines shake. Pines are the hardest sort of tree to live when
shifted to any other soil. And here there's none but the crews cursed clay.
Steady helmsman. Steady. This is the sort of weather when brave hearts snap
ashore and keeled hulls split at sea.
Our captain has his birthmark. Look yonder, boys. There's another in the
sky. Luridlike, you see all else pitch black. Dagu, what of that? Who's afraid
of black's afraid of me? I'm quarried out of it. Spanish sailor aside. He
wants to bully, huh? The old grudge makes me touchy. Advancing I, Harpoonir,
thy race is the undeniable dark side of mankind. Devilish dark at that. No
offense, Dagu grimly. None. St. Jaggo's sailor. That Spaniard's mad or drunk,
but that can't be, or else in his one case, our old mogul's firewaters are
somewhat long in working. Fifth Nantucket sailor. What's that? I saw
lightning. Yes. Spanish sailor. No. Dagu showing his teeth. Dagu springing.
Swallow thine mannequin. White skin, white liver. Spanish sailor meeting him.
Knife thee hardly. Big frame. Small spirit. All. Arrow. Arrow. Arrow.
Fashego with a whiff. Arrow alo. and arrow a loft. Gods and men both brawlers.
Belfast sailor. Around a virgin be blessed. Around plunge in with
you. English sailor. Fair play. Snatch the Spaniard's knife. A ring. A ring.
Old MS sailor. Ready formed. There the ringed horizon. In that ring Cain struck
Abel. Sweet work. Right work. No. Why then God mates thou the ring? Mate's
voice from the quarter deck. Hands by the howiards in top gallon sails. Stand
by to reef top sails. All the squall the squall jump my jollies. They scatter.
Pip shrinking under the windless.
Jollies. Lord help such jollies. Crish crash. There goes the Blang wang.
God. Duck. Lower. Pip. Here comes the royal yard. It's worse than being in the
world woods the last day of the year.
Who'd go climbing after chestnuts now?
But there they go all cursing. And here I don't. Fine prospects to them. They're
on the road to heaven. Hold on hard.
Jiminy, what a squall. But those chaps are worse yet. They are your white
squalls. They white squalls. White whale. Sure. Sure. Here have I heard all
their chat just now. And the white whale. Sure, sure. But spoken of once,
and only this evening. It makes me jingle all over like my tambourine.
That anaconda of an old man swore him in to hunt him. Oh, thou big white god, a
loft there somewhere in yawn darkness.
Have mercy on this small black boy down here. Preserve him from all men that
have no bowels to feel fear.